Jan de Hartog Papers, 1943-2005
University of Houston Libraries
Jan de Hartog Papers
1933-1979
De Hartog, Jan, 1914-2002
Jan de Hartog (1914-2002) was a Dutch born author and playwright. The Jan de Hartog Papers consist of manuscript material, correspondence, scrapbooks, photos and other material documenting De Hartog's life and career. The papers are divided into three series: Works, The Hospital Materials, and Career.
4 boxes and 3 oversized boxes; 7 linear feet
1967-002
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Jan de Hartog was born in Haarlem, Netherlands on April 22, 1914. His father, Arnold Hendrik, was a theologian; his mother, Lucretia Meijjes de Hartog, a scholar of medieval mysticism. He attended Amsterdam Naval College, and worked as a sailor, war correspondent and naval inspector before achieving success as an author and playwright.
Although de Hartog published five detective novels under the pseudonym F. R. Eckmar in the 1930's, his first noteworthy work was the novel Holland's Glorie (1940). Published in Dutch 10 days before the outbreak of the Second World War, the work sold over one million copies and was regarded as an essential expression of Dutch identity in wartime. The book made him a public figure in the Netherlands, and he used this platform to speak out against German occupation. In early 1942, de Hartog was forced to go into hiding and eventually fled the Netherlands under threat of arrest. After a lengthy journey across Western Europe, he arrived in England in July, 1943.
De Hartog spent the next decade in England, writing novels and plays in English. In 1946, he married Angela Priestly, daughter of English writer J.B. Priestly. One of his first English language works was the play Skipper Next to God, about a captain carrying European Jews to the United States. It debuted in London in 1945 and was later performed on Broadway. The 1951 comedy The Four Poster brought de Hartog his broadest and most enduring success. After runs in London and American repertory theater, its Broadway run, starring Hume Cronin and Jessica Tandy, earned the 1952 Tony award for Best Play. De Hartog collaborated on a French adaptation with the writer Collette, and the work was later adapted as a musical, I Do I Do!, and a television play. His novels of this period included The Lost Sea (1951), The Little Ark (1951), and A Sailor's Life (1955).
His marriage to Marjorie Mein in 1961 led de Hartog to become a Quaker. The couple lived on a 146-ton houseboat for several years before marrying, and first came to Houston on boat travel. In 1962, Jan assumed a residency in playwriting at the University of Houston, during which time the couple volunteered at Jefferson Davis Hospital. As a volunteer, de Hartog was exposed to the horrible conditions facing patients and staff at Harris County's charity hospital. His work, The Hospital, exposes the conditions and treatment received by patients at Jefferson Davis Hospital (later renamed Ben Taub Hospital). His book received national acclaim, drawing attention to needed changes in the charity hospital system in Houston. In the wake of The Hospital's publication, the de Hartogs became a target of threats and unwanted harassment which ultimately led to the couple leaving Houston in 1964.
The de Hartogs remained active in progressive social causes, using the proceeds from The Hospital book to finance aide programs. Further involvement in peace and social justice efforts lead the couple to become advocates of charity to Korean and Vietnamese war orphans, and in the process they adopted two Korean children. He chronicled these events in the 1969 work, The Children.
De Hartog's long and varied career also included having several works adapted for the screen. His novel, Stella (1951), was adapted for the screen with Sophia Loren and William Holden, as was The Spiral Road (1957), which starred Rock Hudson. His other notable works included novels The Captain (1967), The Commodore (1986), a trilogy fictionalizing the history of the Society of Friends- The Peaceable Kingdom (1972), The Lamb's War (1980) and The Peculiar People (1992), The Centurion (1989), and The Outer Buoy (1994).
The de Hartogs returned to Houston in 1993. In 2002, Jan was presented with an Hononary Doctor of Humane Letters at the University of Houston. Jan de Hartog died September 22, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The Jan de Hartog Papers, 1943-2005, consist of manuscript material, correspondence, scrapbooks, photos and other material documenting the life and career of Jan de Hartog (1914-2002). The papers are divided into three series: (1)Works, (2) The Hospital Materials, and (3) Career.
The Works series contains manuscript material, including notes, manuscript and typescript drafts, galley proofs, play scripts, television scripts and dictation tapes for The Captain, The Hospital, William and Mary and various other works. The Captain subseries includes notes, various typescript drafts of the work, the publisher's copy of the work, galley proofs, tape recordings, and page proofs. Many of these items are heavily edited by either the author or the copy editor. The Hospital subseries contains notes, outlines, drafts, and galley proofs of the work. Additional documents relating to the response to The Hospital and to Jan and Marjorie de Hartog's work at Jefferson Davis Hospital is included in The Hospital Materials series.
The Hospital Materials series includes notes, clippings, speeches, correspondence, photos and scrapbooks related to the de Hartogs' Hospital volunteer work at Jefferson Davis Hospital as well as the publication of and response to de Hartog's 1964 book, The Hospital. Outgoing correspondence is arranged by date; incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically. An index of correspondents is available; contact Special Collections for more information.
The career series contains clippings, correspondence and commemorative material related to de Hartog's writing, teaching, and theatrical productions. Books, personal effects, and sound and video recordings have been removed from the papers and cataloged separately. They are accessible through the UH Libraries online catalog in the subfield of "Jan De Hartog Papers".
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition
This collection was donated to the University of Houston Libraries by Jan and Marjorie DeHartog in 1967, with additional accessions in 1970, 1999, and 2005.
Subjects(Persons)
De Hartog, Jan, 1914-2002; De Hartog, Marjorie
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston; Ben Taub General Hospital; Jefferson Davis Hospital (Houston, Tex.)
Formats
Correspondence; Typescript Drafts; Galley Proofs; Manuscript Drafts; Photos; Audiotapes; Clippings
Detailed Description of the Papers
- I. Works, 1943-1979 and undated
  - The Captain, 1940-1966 and undated (Box 1)
    - Early Draft as The Professor, 1950 (Box 1)
      - Typescript,undated (Box 1)
      - Notes,undated (Box 1)
    - Early Draft as Tug of War,undated (Box 1)
      - "Notes on the Arctic", undated (Box 1)
      - "Working Notes",undated (Box 1)
      - "Resume and Project Notes", undated (Box 1)
      - "Final Work Sheets",undated (Box 1)
      - "Corrective Notes",undated (Box 1)
      - "Jan's Corrected Copy", Typescript with corrections,1966 (Box 1)
      - Carbon copy with corrections,1966 (Box 1)
      - Publisher's copy, photocopy, 1966 (Box 2)
      - "Tug of War,, read by the author, sides 1&4", audiotape, 1966 (Box Tape 1)
      - "Tug of War, read by the author, sides 2&3", audiotape, 1966 (Box Tape 2)
    - The Captain, (1966) (Box OS 1)
      - Galley Proofs,1966 (Box OS 1)
      - First page proofs,1966 (Box OS 1)
      - Second page proofs,1966 (Box OS 1)
      - "Tape recording sample", typescript 1968 (Box 2)
    - The Captain (Screenplay), photocopy with corrections, undated (Box 2)
  - The Hospital, 1962-1965 and undated (Box 2)
    - "Jefferson Davis Emergency Room - a record", Typescript with annotations, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - "Notes and Work Plan", 1963 (Box 2)
    - "Worksheets", 1963 (Box 2)
    - First draft, carbon copy, 1963 (Box 2)
    - First draft, carbon copy with corrections, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Second draft, carbon copy with corrections, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Final draft, carbon copy with corrections, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Printer's proof, carbon copy with corrections, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Printer's proof, carbon copy with corrections, 1964 (Box 3)
    - "Throw-outs", typescript with corrections, carbon copy with corrections, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - "Final revision", typescript, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - Uncorrected proof, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Other Works,1943-1979 and undated (Box 3)
    - The Artist (Story), photocopy with corrections, undated (Box 3)
    - The Bomb (Story), typescript, undated (Box 3)
    - The Four Seasons (Notes), photocopy with corrections, undated (Box 3)
    - The Great Fire (Story), photocopy, 1979 (Box 3)
    - My Lord, What a Morning and Little Doris (Story), photocopy, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Miracle of the Seahorse (Play), photocopy, undated (Box 3)
    - Native in a Nightshirt (Story), typescript, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Now Let Us Try What Love Will Do (Television Script) (Box 3)
      - Script, photocopy, undated (Box 3)
      - Notes on locations in Philadelpia, photocopy,undated (Box 3)
    - Red Cement (Play) (Box 3)
      - Script segment, photocopy, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Letter to Robert Everding, photocopy,1978 (Box 3)
    - The Rose Revived(Play), photocopyundated (Box 3)
    - Skipper Next to God (Play) (Box 3)
      - "First English version", photocopy,1945 (Box 3)
      - "Possible later version", photocopy,undated (Box 3)
      - "Letter to Bob Everding", photocopy,1979 (Box 3)
      - "Stage Plan", photocopy,1979 (Box 3)
      - Maitre Apres Dieu (Screenplay), photocopy,undated (Box 3)
      - Young Bass of Outstanding Volume: Preface to Skipper Next to God, photocopy,undated (Box 4)
    - Two Wartime Stories: Skim Milk and Little Finger, photocopy1943 (Box 4)
    - A View of the Ocean (Story), photocopy,1943 (Box 4)
    - William and Mary: Story of a Marriage (Play) (Box 4)
      - "In two acts", photocopy,1963 (Box 4)
      - "In three acts", photocopy,1963 (Box 4)
      - "Worksheets", typescript with corrections,1963 (Box 4)
      - "Final Script", typescript,[ca. 1963] (Box 4)
      - "Radio Script", typescript,1968 (Box 4)
- II. The Hospital Materials,1962-1966 and undated
  - Scrapbooks, 1962-1964 and undated (Box 4)
    - "Houston" (Box OS 2)
      - Dust jacket and packaging,1964 (Box 4)
      - Clippings,1964 (Box 4)
      - Television transcripts,1964 (Box 4)
      - Radio transcripts,1964 (Box 4)
      - Church calendar,1964 (Box 4)
      - Meeting minutes,1964 (Box 4)
      - "Debbie and Gus to JDH", telegram1964 (Box 4)
      - Zest Magazine,1964 (Box 4)
    - "US and Abroad" (Box OS 3)
      - Newspaper Clippings,1964-1965 (Box 4)
      - Magazine Clippings,1964-1965 (Box 4)
      - Publicity Materials,1964-1965 (Box 4)
      - Carey-Thomas Award Certificate,1965 (Box 4)
    - "Holland" (Box OS 4)
      - Clippings1965 and undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous and duplicate clippings, photocopies, 1964-1989, undated (Box 4)
  - Speeches (Box 4)
    - Live Oak Friends Meeting,1962-1965 (Box 4)
    - Capping Address,1964 (Box 4)
    - Address to the Ben Taub Nurses' Aides Corps,1964 (Box 4)
    - Address to the Jefferson Davis School of Nursing,undated (Box 4)
    - "Hospital Speech" cue cards,undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Outgoing Correspondence,1963-1966 (Box 4)
    - Incoming Correspondence,1964-1966 (Box 4)
      - A-F (Box 4)
      - G-S (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
      - Unidentified correspondents and fragments (Box 4)
    - Mutual of Omaha Criss Award Correspondence1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Jan de Hartog in Red Cross volunteer uniform, undated (Box 4)
    - Marjorie de Hartog in Red Cross volunteer uniform,undated (Box 4)
    - Marjorie de Hartog with infant, undated (Box In frame)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - "Hospital and Community", typescript, undated (Box 4)
    - Red Cross, Houston-Harris County Chapter, pamphlets, 1964, undated (Box 4)
    - "Handbook for Volunteers: Houston-Harris County Chapter American Red Cross Nurses' Aide"undated (Box 4)
    - "The Trojan Women, Benefit Premiere for Citizen's Fund for Voluntary Nursing", theater program, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Mercy Fund List of Contributors, carbon copy,undated (Box 4)
- III. Career, 1962-2005 and undated
  - "Outline for a program for a dramatic workshop, University of Houston", typescript,1962 (Box 4)
  - Clippings,1962-1967 and undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: (Box 4)
    - Marsha and Warren Hollman, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Compassion and the Art of Medicine, Response from medical students, manuscript, typescript, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Plaque inscription, note from Marjorie de Hartog,2005 (Box 4)